UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

Drew E. Winters, PhD.

www.drewEwinters.com drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu

Biographical sketch

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

Education

Education			
University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO Post-Doctoral Fellow: Developmental Psychobiology			Current
Research Group (DPRG)			
- Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph S	Sakai, M.D.		
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN	. – Ph.D.		April 2020
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN	-MSW		May 2016
Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN.	– B.S.		May 2013
Certifications			
Machine Learning Using Scikit-Lear	Machine Learning Using Scikit-Learn in Python – Inira		
Data Scientist in Python - DataCamp	p		Nov 2021
Computational Neuroscience – Neur	romatch Aca	demy	July 2021
Data Scientist in R – DataCamp			April 2020
Multilevel Modeling II Advanced To		M	Oct 2020
Network Analysis II Advanced Topi			Oct 2020
Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Variables – EITM		Oct 2018	
Academic appointments			
University of Colorado	Statistician		2021-2022
University of Colorado	Post-Doctoral Fellow		2020-Present
Indiana University	Adjunct Professor		2017-2020
University of Michigan	Teaching Assistant		2019 & 2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Analyst		2018-2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Assistant		2016-2020
Indiana University	Indiana University Research Assistant		2014-2015
Hospital, government, or other professional positions			
UCHealth Encompass program - Aurora, CO		Therapist	2020-2021
Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN		Therapist	2016-2020
Rogers behavioral health – Skokie IL		Behavioral Therapist	2014-2016

Honors, special recognitions, and awards

Postdoctoral Association Travel Award	2021
University of Colorado, Aurora, CO	

Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models	2021			
Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models	2021			
Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics	Statistics Wastery	2021		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models	 Statistics Mastery 	2018		
Structural Equation Modeling with Latent M				
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychology		2018		
ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social Resolution Indiana University Travel Fellow	earch Ann Hardor, MI	2017-2019		
	-11h-:			
Graduate Professional Student Government Fe	enowsnip	2016		
Miranda Pang Endowment		2014		
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Society		2013		
Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Academ	ic Honor Society	2013		
Hellen I. and Rodney E. Nern Scholarship		2013		
Membership in professional organizations				
Society for the Scientific Study of Psychopath	ıv (SSSP)	2022-current		
Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psyc		2020-current		
Society for Social Work and Research (SSWR		2017-current		
society for social work and resourch (SS W)	•	2017 Carrent		
Major Committee and Service Responsibilities				
Board of Directors, National Association of A	Icohol and other Drugs	2011-2018		
of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indian				
Licensure and board certification	Times and heard and the			
License	Contified	Descrified		
	<u>Certified</u>	Recertified		
Licensed Social Worker – Colorado	7/2020	7/2021		
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019		
Review and referee work				
Ad Hoc Reviewer				
Translational Psychiatry	2023			
Neuroimage	2022			
Emotion	2022			
Journal of Drug Issues	2022			
Addictive Behaviors Reports	2022			
Brain Imaging and Behavior	2022			
Cerebral Cortex	2022			
Neuroscience Letters	2021			
Psychophysiology	2021			
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence		2021		
Journal of Juvenile Justice		2018		

Open-Source Software Packages

Mindfulness

Journal of Child and Family Studies

resmod. A python package that derives interaction terms using centered residuals https://pypi.org/project/resmod/, role: author

fsub_extractor. A python package that ties diffusion and functional brain data together. https://github.com/smeisler/fsub_extractor, role: contributor

2017

2016

Invited extramural lectures, presentations and visiting professorships Winters, D.E., Massey, S., Sakai, J. T., Adolescent substance use in response to social consequences of use: The role of empathy. Research Society on Alcoholism, Bellevue, WA.	June 2023
Winters, D.E., Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2023
Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M., Computational Lesioning of Heterogenous Functional Connectomes Explains Variance in Adolescent Callous-Unemotional Traits. Neurohackadamy, University of Washington, Seattle, WA	July 2022
Sanchez, C.R., Cooley, J.L., Winters, D.E. , Ricker, B.T., & Fite, P.J. <i>Prospective associations between forms of aggression and peer victimization: The moderating role of prosocial behavior</i> . Biennial Research Conference on Relational Aggression, Virtual Conference.	July 2022
Winters, D.E. , <i>Introduction to R for medical students</i> . University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Cognitive Load Sensitivity Impacts Theory of Mind Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Traits. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Youth with Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Control. American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Juan, PR	Dec 2021
Winters, D.E., Network typology of adolescents with callous- unemotional traits. Department of Psychiatry Poster Session, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	March 2021
Winters, D.E., Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affective Theory of Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	March 2021
Winters, D.E., Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2021
Winters, D.E. , <i>Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its Impairments in Adolescents</i> . Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	Oct 2020
Winters, D.E. , <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity Score Matching</i> . Training the Indiana Department of Children Services data analysis and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.	March 2020
Winters, D.E., Secondary data analysis. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2020
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy in Clinical Practice. Advanced clinical practice, Dr. Vincent Starnino, instructor. Indiana University School of Social Work,	June 2017

Indiana	<u>1i</u>	INI
Indiana	pons,	IIN.

	meranapons, 114.		
	Winters, D.E . <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Presentation to staff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianapolis, IN.		Aug 2016
	Winters, D.E. Mindfulness in Clinician Self-Care, and Clinical Practice. Presented to the staff and honor society recipients of Chi Eta Sigma for marriage and family therapist. Purdue University.		April 2016
	ching record ndiana University School of Social Work – Teaching A	Aggigtant	
	•	Online	Summer 2017
	S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	
	S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Seminar	Spring 2017 Fall 2016
U	niversity of Michigan – ICPSR		
	Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Online	Summer 2020
	Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Seminar	Summer 2019
Ir	ndiana University– Adjunct Professor		
	S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2020
	S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2019
	S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2019
	S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2018
	S517 Assessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar	Summer 2018
Men	 toring Neuromatch Academy – Computational Neuroscience M I mentored a group of five participants in the conneuroscience track on completing capstone projections. 	mputational	2022
Gabriel Yepes, M.D. – Research Mentor - I mentored Dr. Yepes on conducting research and writing manuscripts resulting in one research publication.			2021
Grai	nt support		
Developmental Psychobiology Endowment. Project title: 'Cognitive control limitations amongst adolescents with callous-unemotional traits that impact the capacity for theory of mind: Evidence from a dual-task paradigm.' Funding amount \$7,355 <u>Role</u> : PI			2023 – 2024
Developmental Psychobiology Endowment. Project title: 'The effects of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst early adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and typically developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI		2021 – 2022	
	National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopatholo Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow		2020 – present
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Waiver A93-3-13-4F-C0-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University School of Medicine. Role: Research Analyst		2019 – 2020	

Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Waiver A93-3-13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University School of Medicine. Role: Research Assistant

Bibliography

Published

Open science legend: * = preregistered; + = analysis code shared; # = data shared Published Peer-Reviewed Articles

- **Winters, D.E.**, Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (In Press) Resting-state connectivity underlying cognitive control's association with perspective taking in callous-unemotional traits. *Psychiatry Research: Neuroimaging*.
- Winters, D.E., Massey, S., Sakai, J.T., (In Press) Adolescent substance use outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy. *Journal of Drug Issues*. DOI: 10.1177/00220426231159303
- *+# Richie-Halford, A., Cieslak, M., Ai, L., Caffarra, S., Covitz, S., Franco, A.R., Karipidis, I.I., Kruper, J., Milham, M., Avelar-Pereira, B., Roy, E., Sydnor, V.J., Yeatman, J.D., The Fibr Community Science Consortium (**Drew E. Winters**), Theodore D. Satterthwaite, Ariel Rokem (2022) An analysis-ready and quality-controlled resource for pediatric brain white-matter research. Scientific Data, 9(1): p. 616.
- + **Winters, D.E.**, Hyde, L. W. (2022). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy. *Journal of Affective Disorders*.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (2022) Emotion identification for self and other associated with callous-unemotional traits and sex differences in early adolescents. *Child Psychiatry & Human Development*.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. DOI: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429
- **Winters D.E.**, Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical, 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- Winters D.E., Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- Winters, D.E., Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with

- adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. DOI: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- Winters, D.E., Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

Published Book Chapters

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

Unpublished

Under Review

- *+ Winters, D.E., Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (under review) Efficiency of heterogenous functional connectomes explains variance in callous-unemotional traits after computational lesioning cortical midline and salience regions
- *+ Winters, D.E., Guha A., Sakai, J.T. (under review) Connectome-based predictive modeling of empathy in adolescents with and without the low-prosocial emotion specifier
- *+ Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Cognitive processes underlying prosocial decision making in callous-unemotional traits.
- + Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., **Winters, D.E.**, Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial

Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.

Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review) Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the mediating role of cognitive control.

In preparation

Winters, D.E., Connectome-based data-driven subgroups association with theoretical groups of callous-unemotional traits and low prosocial emotion specifier